Great thanks for the introduction.
Great talks.
Everyone else, I'm delighted to be here.
I'll share my screen in just a minute.
But I have a big thing
I wanted to show just in my hand.
So subcutaneous is a novel
by Aaron Reed that came out in 2020.
Many of you might already be familiar
with Aaron, read his work,
and maybe this novel itself,
which he actually spoke about at the 2020
ello conference,
which was also hosted by Florida
and online, wasn't supposed to be online
that year,
but subcutaneous is a queer
coming of age novel.
The narrator is an introverted
college student
whose love for his closest
friend, Nico, goes unrequited.
Subcutaneous is also a horror novel.
Ryan and Nico discover a vast basement
under their dilapidated off campus
house that branches into parallel worlds,
which they get lost in.
And most importantly for today,
subcutaneous is an experimental novel.
It's human written
but procedurally generated,
and no copy is the same as any other copy.
So the printed book, like what
I have here, or if you have an e-book
somewhere, it will read as a singular,
cohesive, linear textual object.
Nothing inside indicates
that the novel is variable,
that every copy of subcutaneous
is different.
So Aaron actually gave the keynote
at that 2020
Yellow Conference, and in that keynote
he explained how subcutaneous
worked at a kind of high level.
This is directly from Aaron.
Each time a book is ordered,
a different version of the text
is rendered from a source text
containing many possible variations
of individual words, sentences,
and even entire scenes all come together.
And then there are
thousands, actually hundreds of thousands
of possible variations.
And at any given moment,
any reader only has access
to the ones
that are in their copy of the book.
Also at the 2020 conference,
Andrew Ferguson gave a talk
about how he taught subcutaneous,
in which he had all of his students order.
You know,
they each had their own copy of the book,
and they would spend the first couple
of minutes of class
actually like comparing their copies
with each other.
And it was kind of thrown off track
because they had to do it online
because they were on zoom.
So it didn't have quite the same feel.
But one of the things that Andrew said
in his talk is that subcutaneous,
because every copy is so different
from each other, it defies one of the
hallmark tools of textual scholarship,
which is the very aurum,
which is where you compare
multiple copies of a text side by side.
And when I taught subcutaneous
a few years later, I did the same thing
Andrew did inspired by him.
We were actually in person,
and we did get to compare the copies
next to each other,
and students were often amazed
at how wildly some of the variations
were, and also how subtle
some of the variations were. And
I enjoyed it.
It was great.
Aaron actually spoke to the class,
he zoomed in
and it was a really good class.
But I still are sequencing classes,
but I still wish we had been able
to dive deeper into the like,
the variance of the novel,
and a more systematic way
using the tools of textual scholarship.
And I also wish
that we had kind of engaged with the novel
on the level of code,
because Aaron has made the source code
available for the novel.
Flash forward to 2025.
Aaron
actually released the entire source code
into the Creative Commons domain,
along with 10,000 copies of the novel
and the ability
to generate your own copies of the novel
and do whatever you want with them,
as long as you attribute Aaron with with
you no credit.
So that kind of set the stage
for me to do what Andrew Ferguson had
said was kind of impossible,
which is make a subterranean variorum.
So that's what I want to show you.
My screen.
Okay.
I see people not in their heads.
So let me get the.
So this is the very warm
and at its default stage, it's
basically you can look at two copies
of the text side by side.
And you can look at them this way.
And I have preceded it with
25 different variations
that I generated myself.
Now that the code is there to generate.
And so we can compare them side by side.
But what's really I think
powerful is
I have all these different modes.
So there's like this track changes mode.
Let me actually compare
these two seeds in chapter two.
So track ages is like
we're looking at a word document
or a GitHub diff
between two versions of code.
You can see the variations between these
two different, these two different seeds.
And for instance down here we can see that
one seed uses the word hangover
and another uses the word memory.
And that just subtle variation actually
changes how we understand the narrator.
Ryan.
Similarly,
the next paragraph we have about Nico
and we know we hear about what Nico spends
his time doing with his buddies.
He's either
playing baseball or basketball
with his philosophy or board game buddies.
And those two kind of,
I mean, hate to kind of
delve into stereotypes,
but those two like knowing whether
Nico hangs out with philosophy
people or board game
people can kind of shape
our understanding of Nico.
So this is the kind of track changes
view.
We can do a correlation view
where we can actually look
on a paragraph level
to see the differences.
So let me just jump to chapter six.
No, actually chapter 16.
Did my screen just get big.
Yeah.
So chapter 16
you can see it on a paragraph level.
What is different
between these two seeds.
So the blue paragraphs are unique
to see 2020
6006 60,021.
And if you if you read this text,
you can see that it's very grounded in
the material realm, in the material world.
So again, that shapes our sense of
the narrator
and all sorts of other views.
So I said I wanted to be able to kind of
engage with the underlying source code.
So under the analyze panel we can.
We can
now there are these little brackets.
And we can click on any paragraph
and we can see the underlying source code.
And some of them have a lot
more going on than others.
We can see
all the variables that are that at work.
There are these
kind of system wide variables
that thread throughout the entire novel,
and we can kind of pinpoint them
where they're working, what they're doing.
So this project was really made
with critical
code studies scholarship in mind.
There is a word differential.
So you could see what words are unique
to the seeds that you have online.
And then you can click on the word
and see it in context.
So just again a lot of tools to read
and kind of understand
and do research on the novel.
I was really interested
in making visualizations as well.
So under the analyze we have
a heat map that shows like which chapters
of the two seeds that you have up
have the most variation between them.
And then again, you can click on the the
the bar
and go to the chapters in question.
But I have
some more
kind of narrative visualizations as well.
This one actually shows
how the the 25 seeds that are in here,
how they kind of vary across
different plot points,
and you can click on a single one
and you can kind of follow through.
Another is.
This also kind of walks
a reader through the, again, kind of
plot points?
My my zoom control is like over writing.
It's on top of my control controls here.
So again, we can kind of click through
and there's these explanatory
text down here that help either
spoilers in here.
So I wouldn't do this with students
or you know before you read the book.
But it can it kind of walks
through these major plot points
and tells you how many variants are in
that do that.
So that's one I go back.
Four more minutes.
Okay.
So just another, another visualization,
a couple more visualizations.
There's a final kind of boss battle
that happens,
and there are multiple variations
of how it can take place.
So I'm using three.js
to kind of do a visualization
of how the boss battle can unfold.
And you can just kind of see it
narrowing down.
And then again, you can click on
any one of one of these seeds,
and it will link
you back to the to that text in context.
I also wanted to convey a sense because,
I mean, you can
you can generate thousands of variations
in that overwhelming
feeling I have created.
So there's the Gonzo method
where you can see all 25 seeds,
like next
to each other and scroll through them.
But I had real fun making a cave.
This kind of immersive
virtual reality version
where you're like, in a room
and you can see all the variations
next to each other
and you can scroll through them.
And again, this is not you're
not going to read the novel this way.
Like, that's not the point of this.
The point is to have a kind of
visceral reaction
to how how overwhelming the text is.
And this also plays
with some of the themes of the novel,
which is about, in some ways
a claustrophobia.
And things along those lines.
I have a whole bunch of research
tools built in, so you can
you can double click any paragraph
and leave an annotation on that paragraph.
Note here, these notes are all saved
in your local browser's storage.
So they're kind of like, I can
come back to it later and click this note.
But if I were a teacher,
I could do a bunch of notes,
and then I can export them
and then exports as a JSON file.
My students could upload them
and see all of my research notes.
I could like, have questions for
my students about different paragraphs.
There's deep links,
so any paragraph can be deep linked out.
You can bookmark current views and so on.
The final thing I want to talk about in
just the last few minutes is
because Aaron released
the code as a Creative Commons license.
You can still buy the book version,
and I encourage people
to buy the hard cover or the paperback
cover book version from Aaron, but you can
now freely generate a copy here,
so you can just request a copy by email
and say if you want an additional
like plain text or email version, clicks
submit.
And I have a little system
worked up where
my little computer
running in the background gets this.
Note that you want to want
a version of the novel.
It'll generate a new version that's never
been read before and email it to you.
So again, it makes it really accessible
for folks to do that.
How much time? One minute.
So I'll just say I did not code
all this myself.
This was not vibe coded by any measure
because I was very deliberate.
This took about seven months
worth of work to do,
but I couldn't have done it
without Claude helping me
with a D three.js with all sorts
of other kind of implementations.
It was a very much a back and forth
iterative process with code.
And if we if it comes up in the Q&A,
I'll be happy to talk
about that experience
of vibe of not vibe coding.
But really this is a I think, a
full fledged digital humanities project.
I estimate it would have taken
like a single full time
developer, professional developer,
at least 12 months to do this, and
no one was going to do it like this.
This was not something
anybody was asking for.
It was something I wanted for me
and my students and for the community.
And it kind of lowered
the the coding agents, made it possible
to kind of experiment with something
that otherwise would not have happened.
And I'll be happy to talk about that
or the project or anything in the Q&A.